Julian Busch

I'm a PhD student in computer science at the Database Systems and Data Mining (DBS) group at LMU Munich, working on various topics in machine learning. My research focuses on learning representations of complex data, including graphs and high-dimensional data.

My areas of expertise include, but are not limited to, machine learning, deep learning, data mining, data science, artificial intelligence, big data management and analytics, and algorithm design.

I have 5+ years of research experience and 2+ years of experience working in industry and with industrial partners.







Education

04/2016 - 07/2021 (expected)

Dr. rer. nat. (PhD) Computer Science

LMU Munich, Munich, Germany Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Thomas Seidl

10/2013 - 03/2016

M.Sc. Computer Science

RWTH Aachen University, Aachen, Germany

Minor: Mathematics

Thesis supervisor: Prof. Dr. Thomas Seidl GPA: 3.9/4.0 (German grading system: 1.30)

10/2009 - 09/2013

B.Sc. Computer Science

University of Hamburg, Hamburg, Germany

Minor: Applied Bioinformatics

Thesis supervisor: Prof. Dr. Ulrike von Luxburg GPA: 4.0/4.0 (German grading system: 1.12)

Awarded as best bachelor graduate

Experience

04/2016 - present

LMU Munich - Research Assistant Database Systems and Data Mining Group *Munich, Germany*

04/2019 - 09/2019

Siemens Corporate Technology - Research Intern

Research Group for Big Data and AI Technology for Business Analytics and Monitoring *Princeton, NJ, USA*

11/2018 - 12/2018

George Mason University - Visiting Scholar

Department of Geography and Geoinformation Science Fairfax, VA, USA

05/2015 - 02/2016

RWTH Aachen University - Student Research Assistant

Data Management and Data Exploration Group *Aachen, Germany*

12/2010 - 03/2011

University of Hamburg - Student Teaching Assistant

Discrete Mathematics Group Hamburg, Germany

Industry Projects

Third-party funded research projects at LMU Munich.

03/2018 - 09/2018

Explanation of Classification Results on Multivariate Time Series by Convolutional Neural Networks

Siemens AG

09/2017 - 02/2018

Data-driven Methods for Pre-Ignition Cause Analysis

IAV Automotive Engineering GmbH

Supervised external master theses at LMU Munich.

07/2020 - 01/2021

Federated ClusterGAN: Latent Space Clustering on Decentralized Datasets

Rohde & Schwarz GmbH & Co. KG

Publications

NF-GNN: Network Flow Graph Neural Networks for Malware Detection and Classification

Julian Busch, Anton Kocheturov, Volker Tresp, and Thomas Seidl
International Conference on Statistical and Scientific Database Management (SSDBM), 2020 (accepted)
[pdf]

Learning Self-Expression Metrics for Scalable and Inductive Subspace Clustering

Julian Busch, Evgeniy Faerman, Matthias Schubert, and Thomas Seidl *NeurIPS Workshop: Self-Supervised Learning - Theory and Practice*, 2020 [pdf] [poster] [code]

Ada-LLD: Adaptive Node Similarity for Node Classification Using Multi- Scale Local Label Distributions

Evgeniy Faerman, Felix Borutta, *Julian Busch*, and Matthias Schubert *IEEE/WIC/ACM International Joint Conference on Web Intelligence and Intelligent Agent Technology (WI-IAT)*, 2020

Best Student Paper Award

[pdf]

Grace - Limiting the Number of Grid Cells for Clustering High-Dimensional Data

Anna Beer, Daniyal Kazempour, *Julian Busch*, Alexander Tekles, and Thomas Seidl *Conference on Learning, Knowledge, Data, and Analysis (LWDA)*, 2020 [pdf]

PushNet: Efficient and Adaptive Neural Message Passing

Julian Busch, Jiaxing Pi, and Thomas Seidl
European Conference on Artificial Intelligence (ECAI), 2020
[pdf] [slides] [talk] [code]

Structural Graph Representations based on Multiscale Local Network Topologies

Felix Borutta, *Julian Busch*, Evgeniy Faerman, Adina Klink, and Matthias Schubert *IEEE/WIC/ACM International Joint Conference on Web Intelligence and Intelligent Agent Technology (WI-IAT*), 2019
[pdf]

Semi-Supervised Learning on Graphs Based on Local Label Distributions

Evgeniy Faerman, Felix Borutta, *Julian Busch*, and Matthias Schubert *International Workshop on Mining and Learning with Graphs at ACM SIGKDD (MLG)*, 2018

[pdf]

Towards Learning Structural Node Embeddings using Personalized PageRank

Felix Borutta, *Julian Busch*, Evgeniy Faerman, and Matthias Schubert *Conference on Learning, Knowledge, Data, and Analysis (LWDA)*, 2017 [pdf]

Teaching Experience

Teaching assistance at LMU Munich.

Algorithm Design (Elite master's program Data Science)

Lecture

Winter 2019

Big Data Management and Analytics

Lecture

Winter 2017

Innovation Lab Big Data Science

Practical

Summer 2017

Knowledge Discovery in Databases I

Lecture

Summer 2016, Winter 2018

Knowledge Discovery in Databases II

Lecture

Summer 2020

Machine Learning

Lecture

Summer 2018

Recent Developments in Data Science

Seminar

Winter 2016, Summer 2017, Summer 2021

Software Development Lab

Practical

Summer 2016, Winter 2016, Winter 2020, Summer 2021

Supervised Theses

Bachelor and master thesis supervision at LMU Munich.

2020

Neural Hough Transform for Subspace Clustering

Master Thesis

Generalized Neighborhood Aggregation for Graph Neural Networks

Bachelor thesis

Federated ClusterGAN: Latent Space Clustering on Decentralized Datasets

Master thesis

2019

Neural End-To-End Subspace Clustering

Master thesis

Spatio-Temporal Link Prediction

Bachelor thesis

Inductive Subspace Clustering

Master thesis

Recommendations on Dynamic Heterogeneous Networks with Metapath-RNNs

Master thesis

Deep Conformance Checking

Bachelor thesis

Graph Classification

Bachelor thesis

2017

Dynamically Adapting Vertex Embeddings

Bachelor thesis

2016

Visualizing High-Dimensional Data with t-SNE

Bachelor Thesis

Accelerating Minimax Hierarchical Clustering

Bachelor Thesis

Academic Service

External reviews for academic conferences, journals and workshops.

- **CIKM** 2017, 2020
- Computers and Security 2021
- **DAMI** 2019, 2020, 2021
- DSAA 2018
- ECIR 2021
- EDBT 2018
- ICDE 2018
- **IDEA** 2016
- KDD 2019, 2020
- Machine Learning 2017
- Pattern Recognition 2020

Selected Skills

Languages

C, C++, CSS, HTML, Java, Latex, Markdown, Matlab, Python, R, SQL

Frameworks

Bokeh, DGL, Keras, MLflow, Matplotlib, NetworkX, Numba, NumPy, Pandas, PyTorch, PyTorch Geometric, Scikit-Learn, SciPy, Seaborn, Spark, Tensorflow

Tools

Docker, Git, Linux, Slurm

Soft Skills

Certificate of advanced training in self-management, leadership and teaching skills awarded by the LMU Center for Leadership and People Management

Natural Languages

German (native), English (proficiency), Latin (Latinum), Mandarin (beginner), French (beginner)